design is the art and science by which
we would remake the human presence on
earth and applies to how we provision
ourselves with food energy shelter clean
water materials waste site clean
entertainment health care virtually
everything design is not a typical
discipline the disciplines say of
architecture is a subfield of a larger
subject called ecological design design
typically has been how we make things
but eka logical design is how we make
things that fit that means the Fitness
between an artifact a technology or a
house or a community and the larger
system is the key question and when you
say that you you can't there's a caveat
here because about that larger context
as it plays out over time we're mostly
ignorant about how those bigger systems
over long periods of time work as a
design is always about margins of error
resilience not betting it all on a
single throw of the dice and not
assuming that Robertson charmer once put
it that nature does not play or set
traps for unwary species design is about
caution
it's about precaution it's about harmony
it's about patterns about weaving
systems and strands together in a way
that's durable for long periods of time
but changeable and resilient you
mentioned in your latest book that
design could be conceived as a healing
profession could you say a couple of
things about that
well the humans on the face of the earth
have been something of a oftentimes a
disaster
and it would be difficult to identify
any technology or any human advancement
that didn't move carbon skyward or
seaward the ho primitive tools way back
when started the process by which we
began to tinker with climate we've
accelerated that and that's now an
exponential process so the problem that
we the problem that we have is we've
been digging a hole for ourselves as a
species on this planet for a long time
and in the last fifty or seventy years
the damage has become what appears to be
catastrophic if allowed to go much
further methodological design in that
sense is a healing process it's how we
understand patient earth as Robert
sekolah once put it in a wonderful
thirty years ago and how we understand
ourselves and our own health to be
dependent on the health of the larger
body of Earth Gaia and the idea that the
species can be healthy and prosperous on
a planet run to wrack and ruin uh isn't
just wrong it's a form of mental
derangement that which I don't have any
words do you see the increasing climate
chaos and and the looming scenario of
peak oil as
the end of civilization on opportunity
for a new start and do you think we will
have a powered descent or a crash and
then a rebuilding we don't know that yet
that that's what is at stake that's the
the fork in the road or whatever and one
of the difficulties again with this is
this issue of leads and lags what we
have already initiated in terms of
climate changes we were talking coming
in the door that thirty years of
difference between the emission of the
carbon that amplified the seawater
temperature that amplified the storm
that hit Louisiana we call Katrina but
we don't know where we are no neither do
we know yet how wise intelligent and
farsighted our response can be because
we haven't responded yet which is to say
we've we've been pretty stupid up to
this point so fork in the road well
absolutely
even if we decide to take the fork
toward opportunity we do not know for
sure where the opportunity itself has
passed it may be that that's the fit
that that's the nightmare scenario but I
think we ought to assume that it hasn't
passed that we can make something much
better of this then otherwise would
occur if we simply let nature take its
course and run carbon emissions carbon
levels in the atmosphere to 550 600 800
1000 parts per million that truly would
be the end of civilization by everything
that we know now that would destroy us
so a good question and that's not an
answer that's simply you've defined I
think where we are at this moment
and in the nature of design you speak
about the need to invent or reinvent the
idea of a sustainable human civilization
and then distributed as widely as
possible and as quickly as possible and
this very very much points towards it's
not about nations against nations
anymore it's about the survival of
humanity and on this planet could you
say a few more things about that well
let me just say two things the the issue
sustainability isn't just about
technology and systems and housing and
so forth it will be very much about
it'll be won or lost on on battle of
equity and fairness
there's no sustainable world that could
be made around inequity and there is no
inequitable world that we would want to
sustain anyway the the politics of it
are going to be particularly troubling
it'll be much easier to see how we make
solar collectors then how we make a
solar-powered civilization that's going
to be require a level of political
inventiveness that we haven't seen on
this planet the corporation I think is a
peculiarly maladapted institution it's
adapted to extraction of materials and
to endless economic growth those are
assumptions we can no longer safely hold
and so what the politics will be and a
politics that says that our
great-great-grandchildren have standing
which is to say a right to stop
parts of our behavior that deprive them
in terms of our constitution of life
liberty and property
so sustainability and ecologic InDesign
or about seeming world as a system and
the interconnections over long periods
of time those are two fundamental
changes and they run against virtually
everything that we've done
scientifically and technologically in
the past 300 years our science is
preceded by disaggregation not by
aggregation it's preceded in small steps
without adequate regard for the most
part for the long term but systems of
governance will be the same face the
same challenge we have to understand how
to govern in terms of systems and
patterns over long periods of time to
honor the rights of generations 5 6 7
removed from our own where do you see
the role of grassroots movements like
the permaculture movement and the eco
village movement and shift what's a
sustainable civilization well I think
they're there the the groups I think in
the trenches trying to create patterns
of actual living and livelihood that
will work in such a world but in the
absence of larger changes in a larger
consensus at the very top of society I
think a good bit of that will be wasted
so I see this as not inclusively a
top-down movement that won't work
neither can it be a simply bottom-up
movement there will have to be some
coordination between the upper layers
and the the grassroots organization so I
see that it's critically important for
people to begin to see what life could
be like lived beyond consumption
and live beyond one way the extractive
economy from mine to dump and eco
villages and permaculture and community
supported agriculture and hundreds of
other kinds of related enterprises are
the inventive wing or the inventive edge
or the cutting edge of this movement and
they're important as much as anything
else for what they do to spark our
ecological and social imagination of
possibilities they're necessary to help
build a consensus that this is not
brewing we don't have to go with a
whimper or bang that we we can in fact
live quite well in fact I think better
than we now live in a world that's more
humane that operates at a slower clock
speed that conserves nature and people
and and so forth that that's a better
world but to believe that people will
have to see that we're visual creatures
and that that's important to people see
to be able to understand what is
possible to do and in your latest book
you mentioned that
where is it
[Music]
but our choice is not whether we are
spiritual and or not it's whether our
spiritual energy is directed forth of
authentic and purposes or not mm-hmm
and you also start the book with a poem
that mentions the four elements and
spirit pure fear for work that's my
first credit poetry where do you see the
role of spirit and the sacred the
dimension of the sacred in this oh you
know my sense Daniel is that the humans
are inevitably spiritual and the
question again is not whether we are but
whether we are authentically spiritual
or not it bubbles out of us where we're
creatures were meaning seeking creatures
and if my highest meaning in my life is
soccer I will make soccer my religion
and it will orient my life it will give
my life meaning and gravity and purpose
and direction it just happens to be a
bad religion I could make
environmentalism a religion that happens
to be a bad religion we can't help but
make something into a belief system and
you can argue why this is for us but
this this goes back to cave paintings
this is part of humanity as soon as we
can identify a human species we see the
species trying to go what does this mean
where are we how did we get here who are
we
you see these questions being asked they
pop up in early philosophy early art
this didn't this is what it means to be
human what what the consumer and the
economic driven the the economy driven
world did was to assume away
spirituality of any kind of authentic
kind and it said that the world is
purely secular and we can satisfy human
needs and wants by purely secular means
but we have it on high authority that
we've been to live by bread alone and
you find this this kind of desperate
search for meaning in the modern world
we had to invent words like a Nomi and
meaning ruthlessness that was Emile
Durkheim and we have all kinds of
behavior patterns that show the need for
authentic beliefs the need for authentic
work not just a job but good work work
that fits a larger scheme of meaning and
the modern world has a surface of stuff
but is posed as a level of meaning
we're long on means but it's short on
ends as somebody once put it which is a
different play on those words but
for this to be authentically religious
we will have to do something that is
incredibly difficult to do we'll have to
decide not just how we make ourselves
sustainable but why we should be
sustained that's a much more difficult
thing there is an old Islamic tale a
tale the gin in which the animals have
humans on trial and it was retold by
Joanna Macy and Jonathan seed in a book
the title which I can't recall but
so I'm thinking like a month is that it
they retell this and I have my students
sometimes do this I just wrote a column
on this it comes out of conservation
biology but it their column simply
called the trial then we the open
chapter and the new book I'm working on
but imagine being in the dark and having
tenir the attorney for the human species
what case would you make to all the
critters who have been rendered sentient
and given voice how would you defend
humankind and I think there can be there
is a defense it can be made but I think
we have to make it and we have to
understand not just that we can survive
here with all these if we'd all agitated
for just smart enough but that we are
good enough to deserve longevity and I
think the the point of that exercise is
simply this that if we knew why we
should survive we would better
understand I think how we might survive
and so it's not an idle debating
question and it takes you to the core of
spirituality what do we owe how are we
obliged what do we owe to the far
distant future what do we owe to the
distant past what does it mean for us to
be stewards or trustees and that takes
you back if you push those questions
back far enough who are we what are we
was our role here on a planet simply to
dig up carbon and release it to the
atmosphere and then expire it was that
what we were all about I don't think so
I think there's a higher destiny waiting
for us but that that means that for us
we will have to find common ground
politically morally and spiritually and
that doesn't mean all believe the same
thing it means a common ground of
tolerance acceptance forgiveness love
compassion before we can find the higher
ground by which we might survive that
higher ground let's call it
sustainability or whatever whatever term
fits but the task of finding common
ground in the very best that humanity
has been and the best that we can be and
that in every way is going to be a
spiritual task it will not be a
technological kind of thing and it will
happen one final note here I think that
it will happen with the level of
spiritual leadership rather like a
Gandhi or Desmond Tutu or Martin Luther
King who is able to articulate a level
of reality that is impossible to
articulate if we only focus on
materiality if our debate goes no
farther than the language of
neoclassical economics we're done for
because you can't make an economic
argument for human survival you have to
make a spiritual argument for human
survival we're worth it and we're worthy
in that higher sense
you